New York Ophthalmological Society Records
New York Ophthalmological Society Records
1864-2007
New York Ophthalmological Society
2 linear feet (2 cartons)
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Historical Statement
The New York Ophthalmological Society first met on March 7, 1864. The founders were Cornelius R. Agnew, Herman Althof, Freeman Bumstead, William R. Carmalt, John H. Hilton, Henry D. Noyes, D. B. St. John Roosa, Henry B. Sands, Francis Simrock, and William Stimson. Membership was limited to 44 men and meetings were held on the second Monday of the month, except June through September. Over time, meetings moved from the homes of host members to local hotels and clubs. Scientific sessions involved the discussion of cases and, in later years, the examinations of patients.
The Society is still in existence and is the oldest ophthalmological society in the United States.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection is made up of minutes; correspondence and other documents are found interspersed in some of the minutes. In addition to correspondence, ther materials include membership proposals, obituaries, and financial records.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
New York Ophthalmological Society; Ophthalmology -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.
Container List
- New York Ophthalmological Society Records
  - Record Book, 1864-2007 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume I, 1869 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume II, 1869-1878 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume III, 1878-1885 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume IV, 1885-1890 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume V, 1890-1899 (Box 1)
  - Minutes Volume VI, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1909-1923 (Box 1)
  - Notebook, 1910-1914 (Box 1)
  - Duesbook, 1915-1954 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1923-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1925-1927 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1928-1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Minutes, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1977-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1864-1906 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bills, 1864, 1884-1913, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Obituaries and Case Reports, 1868-1914, [1928]-1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Officer and Members' Lists, Minutes, By-Laws Revisions, etc., 1901-1914 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, Letters of Resignation, etc., 1864-1914, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, Obituaries, etc., 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Membership Proposals, 1929-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Membership Proposals, 1958-1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Membership Proposals, Correspondence, etc., 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Membership Proposals, Correspondence, etc., 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Officer and Member Booklets, 1974-1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Minutes, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Minutes, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 30)
Provenance
New York Ophthalmological Society.